#大家好 我們現在到了信豐安西
Hi everyone! We are now at Anxi in Xinfeng county.
#贛南臍橙產業園
to visit the Gannan Navel Orange Orchard.
#兄弟臨時有事走開啦 他老婆帶我們進去
My buddy can't be with us he's got something to do. His wife is taking us here.
#這幾顆[SIC]樹 都有三十年啦
These trees, are almost 30 years old.
#對
Yea.
#這裡一大片都是臍橃產業園哦
This whole area is the Navel Orange Orchard.
#他這裡將近有五六千畝 全是種的那個臍橙
It covers almost 6 000 mu of land (1 mu = 666.7 square meter), and grows only navel oranges here.
#這幾坐山種的臍橙 一大片都是
Navel oranges are grown here, the whole area, across several hills.
#我們現在去那個臍橙展覽館裡面看一下
We'll now go to the Navel Orange Museum. Let's take look there.
#這個就是贛州市 整個贛州市
This is Ganzhou City. It shows the distribution,
#各縣臍橙面積分佈圖哦
of navel oranges in each county over the whole city,
#全市有 哇 一百六十八萬畝啊
covering a total of 1.68 million mu of land.
#是不是 個十百千萬十萬百萬
Am I right? One, ten, hundred, thousand, ten thousand, hundred thousand, million.
#一百六十八萬多畝
More than 1.68 million mu.
#你看 這就是我們的縣
Look! This is our county.
#你看 柑橘頪
Look! Citrus.
#全部分下來 好多種品種啊
All species are here.
#現在到了果園裡面呦 看下有沒有快熟的
So we are now in the orchard. Let's see if any oranges are almost ready.
#你看 這些都黃啦 馬上就熟了
Look! They all turn yellow, meaning that they will be ready very soon.
#再過 再過十來天它就熟啦
They'll be ready in, in a fortnight.
#進去看一下
Let's take a look inside.
#哇 你看這些臍橙 都是
Wa! Look at the navel oranges. They're,
#好黃啊
golden yellow.
#現在還不是採摘的時候 要再過
But it's still not the harvesting time. We need to wait,
#再過十多天
wait for a fortnight.
#就可以採啦
before they can be harvested.
#你看這個臍橙
Look at this navel orange.
#不大又不小 這種是最標準的果哦
Not too big, not too small. Just right. Standard size.
#身材剛剛好
Perfect size.
#哇 這裡面更多
Wa! There are even more inside.
#上面還有點青
Those up there are still a bit green.
#再過個十來天它就黃啦
They will turn yellow in a fortnight.
#我們摘個來吃一下
Shall we take one and have a try?
#嗯 可以呀 可以摘呀
Yea, sure! Go ahead!
#摘這個
This one is nice.
#最漂亮的
It's the prettiest.
#有沒有刀
You have a knife?
#我沒帶刀
I don't have a knife.
#沒帶刀
Nor do I.
#沒帶刀我直接這樣剝開
I can just split it without a knife.
#哇
Wa!
#哇 這個肉
Wa! Gorgeous!
#很香啊 香嗎
It smells so good!
Does it?
#香
Really good!
#嗯
Um
#這個分份還是非常足的
And it must be very juicy.
#這個水份是
The juice is,
#好多水份啊 這個
really juicy, you know.
#現在 現在也可以採摘了吧 那麼黃啦
Now, now they can be harvested, right? They are all golden yellow now.
#額 我們國家定的日子是十一月六號
Eh. The date fixed by the government is 6th November.
#那個開始採摘
We can start harvesting from that day.
#哦
Oh!
#正式採摘
Not until then.
#嗯
Um!
#好好吃哦
It's really tasty!
#現在都可以採摘啦 那麼 那麼甜
They can actually be harvested now. They're already, already so sweet.
#看這水份
Look at the juice!
#是啊
Yea!
#相當足的水份
It's really juicy!
#這裡可以看得到
As you can see.
#嗯
Um.
#你看這個 全部是
Look! It's all,
#果肉裡面水份很足哦
pulp filled with juice.
#是啊
Indeed!
#這個 這個皮也非常的薄
And the, the peel is extremely thin.
#這一顆[SIC]樹能長多少近啊 那麼多
How much can such a tree yield? There are so many.
#這顆[SIC]樹
This tree...
#能長兩 兩三百斤
around a hundred, a hundred fifty kilogram.
#兩三白斤
A hundred and fifty...
#這個 這個有八年 八年的樹齡啦
Look! It's eight years, the tree is eight years old.
#哇 這樹幹是好大這樹幹啊
Wa! The branch is huge, this branch.
#這個路小心一點啊 那個 好多草
Watch your steps. I mean, there's a lot of grass.
#這個果齡 果樹的年齡比較大
The age of the fruit, I mean the age of this tree is higher.
#那個 比較茂盛
So you see, it's lush.
#只能這樣鑽過來了
We can just squeeze ourselves under it.
#這沒辦法哦
As you can't chop it,
#又不能把它砍了
that's the only option.
#全是臍橙
All are navel oranges.
#一顆[SIC]樹上都能長幾百斤
There should be hundreds of kilograms from a tree.
#這個是紅臉鴨哦
These are, Muscovy ducks.
#用來 用 用它們來除草
They are here, here for weeding.
#它們的屎也可以放到那個臍 臍橙
Their poops can be put to the na, navel oranges,
#做肥料
as fertilizer.
#它們拉的那個屎啊
I mean the poops of the ducks.
#你看 人工都省了
Look! Much manpower can be saved.
#不用除草的
No more weeding.
#天然的除草機
They're natural weeding machines.
#他那邊還有鵝
There are geese too.
#抓都抓不到
I can't catch them.
#抓都抓不到 跑得太快啦 你不要看它那笨笨的
I just can't catch them. They're running really fast. They look clumsy but they are not.
#你一走過它那去啊
They become super agile,
#馬上很靈活的
once you get close to them.
#它這個肉啊 全都是瘦肉
Their meat, is all lean meat.
#沒有 沒有一點肥肉 吃起來非常好吃
Not, not even a bit fat. So it's really tasty.
#像這個
And this duck,
#養了有那個 三四年啦
has been here for almost four years now.
#你看 這個臍橙 結了好多啊 很多都是標準果哦
Look at the navel oranges. There are so many of them. Many are at the standard size.
#這個稍微小的點的都沒那麼多
You can hardly find a smaller one,
#很少
just a few.
#小一點的
I mean the smaller ones.
#都是很標準的
All are up to standard.
#你看這個臍橙
Look at this navel orange.
#這個 它最標準的這種果
This is, it can be taken as a benchmark.
#它 不大又不小
It's neither big nor small.
#皮很薄的哦 這個
And the peel is thin.
#現在都有 聞的[SIC]到味道啦
Now there is, I can smell it
#裡面的臍橙的果肉味
the scent of the pulp inside.
#很靚的哦 你看 這個也是
It's beautiful. Look! This one too.
#這裡有個更靚的
Here's an even more beautiful one.
#藏在中間
It's hidden inside everything.
#被我掰開來看到啦
But I can still discover it.
#這個樹好高啊 那麼高大 它 多少年啦 這個樹
This tree is very tall, so bulky. How old is it now?
#這棵樹是有 十年啦
This tree is, already ten years old.
#十年啦
Already ten years!
#整整十年 十年才長那麼大一點
A whole decade. But it's just a bit larger.
#這個很大了
It's already huge.
Is it?
#嗯
Yea!
#感覺好 感覺十年的 十年的時間長還那麼小
It's like, a decade, a decade but it's still that small.
#我以為很 長 能 能長很大
I thought it would, it would become very, big.
#這個 像這種產果的話
Well, when it comes to the fruits,
#嗯
Yes
#那個 因為它的幅度比較大又比較有高度的話
I mean, coz it has both width and height,
#可以產兩三百斤
It can yield up to a hundred and fifty kilograms.
#那個
I mean,
#那個果
the fruits.
#那今年的產量很高哦
So the yield this year is high, isn't it?
#今年
This year,
#比往年要稍微低一點 因為今年那個
it is slightly less than the previous years. It's because this year, well,
#水份 啊 雨水量 稍微小一點
the water, I mean, the rainfall is slightly less.
#哦
I see.
#總體產量的話 稍微降低一點點
The total yield. should be slightly decreased.
#這個沒事
Never mind
#這個臍橙特別好吃的 這種臍橙
The navel oranges are exceptionally tasty, you know.
#我們信豐安西的臍橙吶
Our Xinfeng Anxi Navel Oranges,
#是我們整個贛南臍橙
are the best navel oranges,
#裡面最好的臍橙
among all the navel oranges in the whole Gannan (Southern Jiangxi) area.
#水份跟化渣能力 糖度啊
Not only are they juicy, but the texture, and the sweetness,
#那個 比較好
I mean, are also better.
#為甚麼嘞 因為受這個地理環境跟生態 那個
It's because the geographical environment and the ecological conditions are the,
#影響
contributing factors.
#哇 這個很漂亮哦 這個 你看
Wa! This is very pretty, this one. Look!
#這個是很嫩的哦 這個
This is very young and tender, this orange.
#誒 怎麼掉下來啦
Eh? Why did it fall onto by hand?
#那我吃掉它看一下
Let me finish it and see if it's good.
#吃一下 看一下味道怎麼樣
Let me see how it tastes.
#哇 這個皮有點薄
Wa! The peel is quite thin,
#這個皮好薄啊
very thin.
#以前我們吃臍橙都是皮稍微厚一點
The navel oranges that we've always been eating had relatively thicker peel.
#這次
But this time,
#稍微薄一點
it's quite thin.
#嗯 挖到一塊
Um! Got a piece.
#哇 好甜哦
Wa! It's very sweet.
#這個
It's,
#這個真是甜這個
It's really sweet, really.
#都沒帶刀 沒辦法
I know it's clumsy, but I don't have a knife.
#但是用手也行吶
But, my hands are good enough.
#哇 怎麼有 有種淡淡的香味
Wa! How come it has a note of fragrance?
#那種
It's like...
#臍橙味好濃啊 這個
It's really flavourful and tasty.
#這水份夠足
It's juicy.
#這水份好多
Indeed, really juicy!
#好多水
So much juice!
#看上去那麼大
It's looks so big.
#啃了一下
I got chocked.
#看上去那麼大 但沒有甚麼渣的哦
It looks so big, but there's mostly juice inside.
#現在還沒到時間摘哦 就那麼好吃啦
It's still not yet the harvesting time, but it's already that tasty.
#到了採摘的時候啊 那個更好吃
When it's the time, it will taste even much better.
#跟我們家兄弟商量了一下哦
Our buddy has kindly agreed to,
#搞兩百箱來送一下粉絲
give two hundred boxes to our fans.
#都拿最好的來送
Only the best ones will be given.
#就 就這種哦
This one, for example.
#又大
Big and,
#不大不小 剛剛好 就這個
not too big and not too small, just right.
#對
Yup!
#這是最優質的 應該是在那個
These are of the highest qualities. They should be,
#極品 算是極品
premium, classified as premium.
#你看像這個一點疤痕都沒有
Look at this one. There's not even a scar on it.
#而且那個皮 那個
And the peel, you know,
#那個臍橙皮非常的薄 水份一看就非常的足
the peel of the navel orange is extraordinarily thin. I can say with confidence that it must be very juicy.
#你看這個皮膚就像小孩子的這個
Look at the skin. It's just like a child,
#皮膚一樣那麼光滑
whose skin is soft, smooth and tender.
#香不香
Smells good?
#香
Good!
#確實很香
Really good!
#現在你看 現在下雨了 我們要去躲一下雨了
Look! It's raining now. Let's get a shelter.
#我們到另外一個果園看一下 現在下雨了
We'll have a look at another orchard. But it's raining now.
#只能徒步走上去
We can only go on foot.
#車開不上去了
The cars can't get there.
#小心一點啊
Watch your steps!
#哇 好多啊
Wa! A lot!
#還沒熟
But they're not yet ready.
#應該
They should be,
#過大多天應該熟啦
ready in a fortnight.
#這邊應該在山上這個
I think it's because it's on the hill.
#光合作用沒那麼
So the photosynthesis is less, eh,
#那個陽光沒那麼充足
I mean there's less sunlight.
#你看 這個果園裡面的果啊 不是很黃
Look! The oranges in this orchard are, still quite green.
#但是現在也可以吃啦 就是稍微有點酸
You can still eat it, but it might be a bit sour.
#要過十多天之後才能把這個全黃 這個全黃了
In a fortnight, they'll become golden-yellow, all of them.
#直徑到 額 八厘米到九厘米之間
The diameters are always between 8 cm to 9 cm.
#很均勻這個果
The range is small,
#一果園 一果園都是
in the whole, whole orchard,
#這裡一大片都是哦
here everywhere.
#這個
This one,
#皮就相當相當的薄
has a very very thin peel.
#好靚 這個皮
The peel is beautiful.
#哇 這個
Wa! This,
#這個子好靚
this orange is beautiful!
#你看 這個
Look! This is,
#很漂亮的
very pretty!
#這個哦
How about...
#來都來啦
I'm already here anyway.
#雖然不是很黃啦
Though it's still not completely ready,
#但是也要摘一個來吃一下啊
but getting one to have a try is always a nice idea.
#不能 不能白來一趟
I can't, I can't leave empty handed.
#那麼遠
It's so far away.
#哇 這個皮好 也是很薄的 這個皮
Wa! The peel is so, it's also very thin.
#你看 這個皮好薄
Look! The peel is really thin.
#誒呀
Eya!
#好結實啊
It's firm and hard.
#好份肯定很足
It must be very juicy.
#你看那個汁
Have a look at the juice!
#射到我一手都是 這個橘子皮的汁啊
It splashes on my hands. It's the juice from the peel.
#吃的時候就不能這麼剝 要用刀
It's not an example to you. Use a knife!
#我這個是比較粗魯的辦法
I'm showing you a brutal way,
#我又不能隨身帶刀
as I can't carry a knife with me all the time.
#哇
Wa!
#全是汁 搞到手上
My hand is soaked with juice,
#你看
Look!
#不剝啦 就這樣直接咬 開咬
Enough with the peeling. I'll just bite, bite it.
#嗯
Um!
#雖然沒
Though it's not,
#不是很黃
not completely ready,
#但是很好吃哦
it's really tasty!
#很香 你看這個果肉
The scent is great. And the pulp,
#哦 那個果肉
oh, the pulp,
#全是那個
it's like,
#一
batches,
#一lang一lang的
batches of vesicles.
#水分特別足
It's exceptionally juicy.
#這個還是 不 不是最佳的口感
It's still not, not the best texture.
#最佳的口感應該到那個
The texture is the best when, you know,
#它那個皮
the peel,
#黃了之後
becomes golden yellow,
#才是最佳的口感
then the texture is the best.
#剛才你看 還有點青 我都把它摘下來吃了
Just now you see, it's still a bit green. But I've already picked it.
#很有臍橙味
It's very flavourful.
#很好吃哦
Tasty!
#現在都不怎麼酸
I can't really feel any sourness.
#就一點點
Perhaps just a bit,
#酸甜
sweet and sour.
#酸甜的
Sweet and sour.
#這樣
Then,
#這個肚臍眼就不能吃啦 這個肚臍眼
the navel is not to be eaten, the navel.
#再去搞個吃一下
Why not one more?
#我幫你剝
Let me peel it for you.
#剝的太慢啦
You're too slow.
#那裡還有好多啊
There're still a lot!
#真的很甜啊 這個臍橙
It's really very sweet, the navel orange.
#嗯 水份很足
Um! It's juicy!
#對啊 特別足
Really, indeed!
#你看這個皮 好薄啊
Have a look at the peel. It's so thin.
#兩三個毫米
Only 2 to 3 mm.
#這個肉又好肥
And the pulp is round and rich.
#這都是種在大山裡面的
These are all grown in the mountain.
#車都進不來
The cars can't get in.
#下雨了進不來
Not when it's raining.
#如果不下兩的話就可以開的[SIC]上來
We can come by car if it's not raining.
#哇 好多 那裡一大片
Wa! A lot! There everywhere.
#你看一下這個整個 整個種臍橙的環境
Have a look at the, the environment of the whole orchard.
#好多
So nice!
#那個好大啊
That one is huge!
#你看這兩個雙胞胎
Look at the twins.
#哇 摸一摸
Wa! Feel it.
#很靚的哦 這個你看
This is really beautiful. Look!
#黃 黃裡帶 額 黃里帶青 青里帶黃的
Yellow, yellowish, eh, yellowish green, greenish yellow.
#就像那個
It's like...
#還沒成熟
It's not yet ready.
#過幾天
They will be ready,
#過個五六天它就熟啦
in a few days, in a week.
#好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
#現在都天都快黑啦 等下我們
It's getting dark. We need to leave now, otherwise,
#回家都找不到路
we can't even get our way home.
#現在 準備下去啦
Now, ready to leave.
#好 下去下去下去
Alright! Go, go, go!
#哎呀 吃的有點
Aya! I've eaten,
#吃的有點飽哦
I've eaten too much.
#這麼 這麼 這 現在都一點沒有酸味哦
You know, you know, well, it's already not even a bit sourness.